the life experience. So what I realized when I started putting this into book form was that
as a funny motherfucker, I can get away with a lot on stage. But on the page, it calls for
a preciseness that you really can't play with. And so it demanded more of me in terms of fine-tuning
research, in terms of really fine-tuning dialogue, and also just really being much more intentional
about what I'm getting across. When I talk about this book, I took it by stage, hold on, talk about
yourselves. So the other thing that happened, and this, this happens when you are kind of just,
um, when you're in flow, like she just comes to you, you know, like, and it may not happen all at
one time. And so I allow myself to be receptive of like new revelations. And once I actually wrote it
and then got a copy of it and was reading it, it dawned on me that the actual book form is
it's a very different experience than the performance. Um, because it's a different
experience of a book. It's not a typical book. It's not a typical play. I perform on stage in
different methods. I have characters, I have dialogue, I have lecture, I have comedy. And so
this is what the book description says on the back. If you call on your ancestors, what would they think
about the current state of the world? Artistic intellectual, let me in the seal, she's got some
ideas. Originally created as a theatrical piece on the page, what would the ancestors say is a
genre innovating treat that takes on the written form of a high vibrational social media scroll.
Miss seals definitely packages dense content into compact contexts through a variety of creative
methods. Moving seamlessly in and out of standup comedy, characters, lecture dialogue, and prose.
Miss seals answers questions like how did Clarence Thomas become a villain? What does Palestine have
to do with black Americans? Are you the type that Harriet Tubman would shoot if she came back?
And more! Its lessons are enhanced by intricate illustrations, an inspiring forward, and an additional
resources list for readers to further expand their knowledge of the work's themes.
Come through the portal with us and engage in philosophical thought about the black American
past and present, and imagine the actualizing of a new future. So I think what I realized in the text
form is that it allowed me to be able to get across very dense ideas and concepts in a really sharp way
way that if I had written essays, would have been a bit more belabored. And I think one of the beautiful
things about being a standup is you're in spaces, you're in all different types of spaces, whereas like
when you're doing lecture series or you're doing intellectual stuff, you're kind of in like the same
spaces every time. And I got to experience both of that. And what's necessary, I feel now, is being able to provide
different forms of the same level of analysis to people. It shouldn't be like you, if you don't think this way,
then you can't get this access to this analysis. And that's what academia does, right? Academia really puts things
in very specific ivory towers. And it's like, if you don't understand this type of writing, if you don't
understand footnotes, et cetera, et cetera, then you never get pushed to like think beyond the limitations
that you've been at. So you get left out. But that's why the arts are so necessary, because the arts bring
those, they build bridges in ways that, you know, the academia doesn't. So that's why I refer to myself
as an artistic intellectual, because I'm using the art to build bridges to those spaces for people who
kind of get left out of it. And I get left out of it too, because I read so goddamn slow. And I get
distracted. You know, I'm reading the Noam Chomsky, I'm like, this is good, but what's that over there?
You know, I'm in it to win it. I'm like, oh, BJ, you are saying some shit. Oh, look at my cat.
Look at them. Oh my God. So this, this medium allows me to bring people into that in a way
that I feel like is, is more, is diverse for a lot of different palettes. And if you want to know more,
then you can seek out more. And I do have an additional resources in the back of the book
that has films and speeches, lists films and speeches and books and essays, et cetera,
that are, that have been, that are resources that I refer to in the text, but that also are resources
that have helped me in just expanding my knowledge base. And that's something that you just kind of
don't do on a play. Any questions? Hi. Can you talk about the portal? Like, I was really fascinated
from like how we entered the space today and just like, how are we accessing it, creating it? Like,
I know it's like imagination. I know it's like tapping into it, but like, what's your advice on
like how do we get to the portal or how do we even get it open? So that's really what the book talk in a
whole is about. And I just, you just let me know that I need to tighten that up at the end. This is my first
one. Um, the portal opens. Okay. Do you know Harry Potter at all? Yeah. That's making so much easier. Okay.
So the portal is, you know, it opens for you when you need it and it opens for whatever you need it
for. And we as a people, I feel like we need to cohesively understand why we need to move through
a portal. We need to go through, we need to elevate to a different level. And we're down here on a very
base level and we don't even allow ourselves to imagine something better. Our version of something
better is nine times out of 10 material based. And that is also by design. Like that's not shade.
That's not shade. Like we're given less so that that's all we desire, right? We're given not enough
so that literally basic survival feels like we're doing it. It's like, well, no, not really. So the
portal is the opportunity to imagine at the full length of your imagination,
unencumbered by human necessity, unencumbered by human indoctrinations. And that best happens
that usually happens as a child because in the child's mind, before trauma besets and takes
over and we start creating masks to protect ourselves, we start developing, uh, abandonment
issues, daddy issues, all the issues. We are at our most open to receive because we trust.
And I think that's the other thing that capitalism has done. It's really beleaguered us with an
inability to trust. So you can't be free to imagine when you have to look over your shoulder.
And that's why spaces like this are so necessary because we need to have freedom spaces to also
be able to have free thinking. And that's why the internet can be so dangerous because if you're
someone like me, you're always trying to imagine, but the internet demands a perfection.
It demands refinement and you can't get to that without trying. And there's going to be bumps and
bruises, you know, I may hit, you know, and it's like, when you do that, it's seen as error versus
as learning. And so that's why we also need to have more of these in-person spaces where we can have
the opportunity to just think about stuff out loud, say it out loud, and be the portal ourselves.
Does that make sense?
Say it one more time.
What is your house?
What was that?
My people.
Were you always a Ravenclaw?
Always.
See, I had to develop. I was a Gryffindor. Gryffindor is like brute force. And you're like,
we're going to do it! And Ravenclaws are like, relax. We don't even have a plan.
And it is also, you know, fuck J.K. Rowling. Like, be clear.
These people are on faded breath, like, oh, we liked her until now.
Okay.
Another question?
Thank you so much, Amanda. You're so inspiring.
Thanks, babes.
You spoke a lot about courage. And for those of us who want to inspire courage in others,
what advice do you have?
Do you?
Demonstrate courage.
I just feel like at this point, you can't inspire without demonstrating, unless someone
comes to you and asks.
You know, I think we know that folks are not on it.
So you're like, come, let's do courage, guys.
And they're like, bitch.
Like, you know, folks are like, I'm busy.
You know, I have a hair appointment. I can't do courage today.
I don't even know the next time she's going to be free.
Like, I just, I can't.
Yeah, I can't do courage today.
Who's going to be there at courage?
Who all will be there at courage?
I'm tired.
I mean, I had somebody tell me one time, and this one I knew I couldn't date him.
He was like, you know, I was going to go to the protest, but I was in my New Jordans.
I didn't want to crease him.
And, like, I respect that as, like, a sneakerhead, but more so as a person with principle.
I was just like, wow.
And he was already too short for me, so it was, like, not that difficult.
But courage is, to me, the only way that it can be inspired is to be demonstrative.
So the story of Harriet Tubman is that people would get scared and turn back, and then she'd have to pull out a gun and, like, scare them into moving forward, right?
But ultimately, she's demonstrating courage by even being a black person during that era with a fucking pistol.
Like, that wasn't no thing to be seen.
So she's already demonstrating a willingness also to kill somebody.
And even in that moment, that person is like, dang, because if she shoot me, they're going to know she's over here.
So I think it's something that has to be demonstrated also because if you get into the mindset of trying to show people, like, look, this is courage.
Look, look, look.
You just drain yourself.
You know?
Take it from me.
You know, and we are still in such an early phase of decolonizing that folks can't even recognize courage because they don't even recognize the threat.
So you might be doing courage, but they're like, I don't even get it.
Like, you could have also not done that.
And then it's going to piss you off, and now you don't have courage.
You have a case.
You got a case.
So I believe in demonstrating courage.
And in addition, when people come to you and they're like, help me, then I feel like one of the best ways to show courage for folks is to show them concrete examples.
But ultimately, people have to know what their limit is.
What are you about?
You know?
I mean, that's really what it boils down to.
In other places, they're like, I will die for this.
That's just what it is.
Right?
We're not there.
We're at courage level lavender.
Where people say things like, when they see an ICE agent accosting someone, in the comments, they say, they need to sue.
That's where we are.
We are in a lawless nation at this present time.
Like, laws are suggestions at this point.
So to still believe that suing is some extension of protection is bonkers to me, right?
And people are also still, in some ways, looking at folks who express courage as a problem.
Now, that's not new, right?
Because they used to say to Martin Luther King and the boys, like, oh, you're stirring up trouble.
That's not new.
But it doesn't change the necessity at all.
And I think the strongest way to inspire courage is to demonstrate courage.
Boldly, unabashedly, and standing on businessly in black Air Force months.
With a creep.
Well, we'll take one more question, and then, oh, maybe one and a half.
I'll be quick.
How's Hufflepuff?
Interesting.
I rarely need a Hufflepuff.
I love the chat here.
I'm a chickama educator.
Oh, give it up for the educator.
Nice.
How was that going?
I'm a slow reader, too.
Solidarity, my sister.
You are an educator.
Thank you.
And we teach littles.
I teach an art class at a community center to 5th and 7th grade, 5th, 6th and 7th graders, and it's a time.
That's awesome.
Let me just say that.
So I'm all the things, social justice, environmental justice, all the good stuff.
If you were an educator of littles, what would be one thing that would be the focus in your classroom?
I really feel like these kids have to understand what community is.
And not in like a, my community is my mailman.
My community is my crossing guard.
But like community as an action.
And I am working on a children's show that I'm still knocking around in my head that will star the character that we started the show with today.
Her name in the show will be Rara.
And the show is called Rara's Radical Readers.
And every episode, she'll do a book report about a radical children's book, and then she'll sing a song, and then we'll talk to the author.
It'll be a time, y'all.
It'll be a time.
But that's the thing to me that is, that I was missing, and that we, I mean, if you're a millennial, like, you did not know that unless you, like, kind of intrinsically knew it.
But it wasn't, like, taught to you in, like, a very practical way.
Like, I know what community is because I would also go to Grenada.
And on an island, like, there is no other way of existing aside from community, right?
Because, like, if you don't like these people, you're going, what you going to do, drive off the edge?
Like, there's no, like, land mass, you know?
So you've got to make it work.
When there's a hurricane, it doesn't, you can't just, like, call on this other place that didn't get hit, and then within a few hours, you know, they drive some to you.
No, like, you've got to wait for a boat to bring shit, and then they don't bring the right stuff, et cetera.
So in the meantime, in between time, you all have to exist together.
We're seeing that right now in Cuba and Jamaica with Melissa.
And so that, to me, like, what I think the children, the littles have to understand is the practicality of community in a way that excites them, right?
In a way that makes them feel safe, because it has to be a principle of their existence.
And we are just finding this out right now, and it's, like, in a yucky way.
It's, like, a necessity way, which is kind of gross, right?
We're like, we have to have community or else.
When, really, um, and I don't know about you guys, but maybe it's just me.
But, I will leave the children all in the future.
Teach them well, man.
Let them lead the way.
Show them all the beauty they possess inside.
Give them a sense.
It's easier.
Okay.
So, that's my answer.
And I think that looks like working together to make things.
I think it looks like understanding different roles, and that all of those roles are valuable.
Because in this society that we live in, we are very much taught that, like, the person on the screen is the only valuable role.
Um, the person at the front is the only valuable role, right?
And anyone who's ever done anything knows that that's just not true.
Like, it ends up being, oh, like, I'm up here tonight, but there's a myriad of people who made this happen that are valuable for many reasons.
And so, it's really trying to communicate the counter of what they're being taught, which is that all that matters is you.
And we know that that's not the case.
Did you see that somebody collapsed in the White House today?
And this man, did you see that man?
Did you see that man?
That orange man was like, how he gonna collapse when I'm up here?
He looked so irritated.
He looked like a New Yorker when someone commits suicide on the train.
Like, this whole city has no shame in being like, god damn it.
And then they're like, this is why we need universal health care.
Like, that's why?
Okay.
Did that answer the question?
We're taking one more?
Greetings, ma'am.
Thank you, Brisa.
Thank you, Amanda.
This was amazing.
I'm an actor, and so I was really curious about your characters and the character development.
And so, I know this is a one-woman show, but just curious about any collaboration, how you came up with the characters.
Yeah, just the making of it.
So, M.T. Checker Hall has existed for a very long time.
He has been alive in my zeitgeist since 06, 07.
So, he's been around.
He's been in multiple projects.
And I live in New York, and I was in New York at the time.
And, like, that's how little cats around my way would talk.
They'd be like, yo, ma, what's good?
What's really good?
You know what I mean?
And that was also when, like, Dipset was really popping.
And, you know, I was DJing in the club.
And, like, I was just living a very New York existence.
And so, M.T. Checker Hall.
M.T. Checker Hall also became a device to be, like, hyper-masculine in touch with your feminine.
So, I use him a lot of times to talk about things that I wish men would talk about that they often don't.
So, like, one of the videos of his that actually ended up doing really well was I did a video with him saying, like, it takes nothing to protect black women.
Like, it's dumb easy to protect black women.
So, like, if you not, like, come on, fam.
And it was much more eloquent than that.
But so that's M.T. Checker Hall.
And in this particular iteration, originally when I was doing the one-woman show, so this is what I mean by developing it onto the page.
So, originally when I was doing the one-woman show, I just brought him in because I felt like there wasn't a music, like, there wasn't, like, a hip-hop, like, a specific art conversation happening in the piece.
And so he would talk about how he was an M.C. and he was traveling the world.
And then he started, like, talking about different things in his music.
And they were like, nah, you can't talk about that because people want you to just talk about money, hoes, and clothes.
But when I sat down to write it, I realized that it was too loose.
I wanted it to be more precise.
And so I grounded him and put him in a bodega.
And I gave him, he always has his daughter with him.
I connected him to Pac.
And I gave him a much more defined story of expansion where it's not just I got to see the world.
It's that when I got to see the world, I realized I wanted to be radical.
And so I embodied that in my music.
And I changed the name of my album from Cars and Hoes to, what is it?
To Blood on My Mic.
Blood in My Mic.
Like Blood in My High.
And I felt, I just feel much happier with his arc.
Because he actually goes somewhere and lands somewhere.
And we see the story of what it means when you are an artist.
And you actually get to be in a commercial space.
And then you realize that to be in that commercial space, they will tell you what is art.
And then you have to decide, can I stay here?
Or am I willing to lose everything that I got from getting here?
And Chekho in his story says that he was not willing to lose.
And he realized that he was a coward.
And so now he has his daughter and he's trying to make sure that his daughter is actually not a coward like him.
Then you have Clarence Thomas.
So there's a section about Clarence Thomas.
And I realized that I was getting away with just being funny and playing off of the fact that we all can't stand that man.
But that was lazy once I sat down to write it.
And so I ended up having to go back and research Clarence Thomas.
Do you know how annoying that is?
Researching Clarence God dang Thomas.
And so I watched his documentary.
I wasn't going to read his book because that's just a bridge too far.
But luckily the documentary just quotes the shit out of his book.
But it allowed me to address Clarence Thomas beyond just my own limitations.
Because that was not, that's low-hanging fruit.
And that's hack work.
That's laziness.
So if I really want to actually make it about something, then I need to be about something.
And I need Clarence to go somewhere.
And so I had to change it from just clowning Clarence Thomas to, is Clarence Thomas redeemable?
What would it take for Clarence Thomas to be redeemed?
And then I realized that I needed to have him having a conversation with someone who could possibly redeem him.
And then we bring in Frederick Douglass.
Two S's.
And so in order for me to properly have that conversation with these characters, I had to research them more.
I had to read the autobiography of Frederick Douglass.
I had to read the essays of Frederick Douglass.
I had to watch the documentaries about Frederick Douglass.
And so it took these characters out of just being frameworks of things I had been told.
And they now became grounded in their own voices.
And that allowed me as an actor and as a creative to be able to, and more importantly as a comedian,
to be able to find genuine funny that is much wittier and more clever.
And that is also driving us somewhere versus just getting the laugh.
If you're a comic, you can get the laugh.
Like that's easy.
But can you get people to think after they're done laughing?
Does that help?
Did I answer the question?
I can't see you at all.
You said kind of?
I guess I was curious, like the making of it.
Did you do it all by yourself?
Yes.
Did you?
Okay.
I thought you did, but I was just curious to be like,
Oh, no, I would have mentioned them when I was, no, this is all me.
I don't like working with collaborators.
People are annoying as hell.
And folks want to be collaborators until you don't want to use their idea.
And then they feel some type of way.
And then you're like, what are we doing?
So I collaborate in specific ways.
So in the written and in the performance version, there is music.
And so I collaborate all the time with my brother in music, Ray angry.
All I have to do with Ray is to say, I want it to be like, and he's like, got it.
I can literally just move my hand a certain way.
He's like, okay, okay, okay.
Let me get on his roads.
And he, and then you're like, oh my God, that's it.
So we have a kinship that way that shows up in collaboration.
I more so collaborate in the, in the sense that I am not precious about my darlings.
I am willing to be critiqued.
So I will share with folks who I know are going to give me genuine criticism and genuine praise.
And so I will share work with them.
People like James Bland, people like my production partner, Kathea.
And then they will either be like, it needs more, you know, or they'll be like, damn, you can write me, you write me, you know?
So, and I have a beautiful Patreon community, um, the seal squad.
And I, I'm very fortunate to be able to share stuff with them and they are able to, I, the great thing about Patreon is you can tell them when it's not good because they're just quiet.
They're not going to tell you nothing, but that's enough.
Um, so that, so collaborating, you know, I understand Tyler Perry's desire not to collaborate, but sometimes you do need collaborators because you also need experts, right?
So this particular work, I will tell you, it's very streamlined also because I'm creating it at a time in my life where I don't have a lot of resources.
So I, I can't afford to also like do it on a bigger scale and, and make a set and hire somebody who does that, right?
And, and have graphics and hire somebody who does that.
So I literally learned in design the program so I could lay out the book myself because I wanted to also know how to lay out books so that whenever I want to write a book and make a book, I don't got to wait for nobody to do it.
And we are at a time, listen y'all, like, excuse me.
I mean, I wouldn't even be surprised if like we leave here and no one was looking at our phones and then we see that they were burning books on the white house lawn.
Like that's where we're at.
Like, you know what I'm saying?
Like, it's like, that would not shock me because for them, knowledge is power and we look at knowledge and we don't see it that way, but books have always been representative of knowledge.
And I was just reading about how there's books from Timbuktu that people have smuggled out of Timbuktu like for centuries.
You know, there's, there's folks in Palestine who are carrying books with them, every displacement, they are preserving these texts because it matters.
And so it's like, I knew that I needed to put it on paper and I did not collaborate, but I did run into a dude at the post office who was talking to me about what I do.
And then I was like, I'm trying to figure out InDesign and it's killing me.
And he was like, oh, I can help you with that.
And the next day put me on the phone.
I'll put me on the Google, the Googles.
No, fuck Google, but also with a man in Pakistan who helped me.
And he taught me InDesign in 20 minutes, 20 minutes.
When you don't got a lot of language to use, you get real efficient.
Do this, do that, the arrow, click it, open it.
No, not that.
No.
Pressure.
Yes, that's okay.
You see it's great.
Try it again.
So, yeah, collabing is great when it's great.
I say all that to say, I reached that point.
If you're an actor and you're not collaborating, you're missing the point.
People who ask me about what, for advice as an actor, I'm going to always tell you, it doesn't matter about knowing agents and studio people and all that shit.
That will come.
You need to find other creatives who make things because they will always make things.
You need to find directors and writers because they will always make things.
That's how they exist, right?
And I think what we get taught as actors is, like, you need to meet producers.
Producers be full of shit.
And a lot of times, producers are what people do who can't make things.
Ever so often, that's not the case.
But that is, particularly in L.A., everybody's a freaking producer.
Them, their mama, their dog.
Them two dogs is producers.
So you have to collab also because your network has to be made of people who make things, not of people who just look like things.
And that has been the most effective thing for me.
I still work right now to this day with people who I met early on who have never stopped making things.
Ever.
And I'm also one of those people.
I will always make things.
Does that answer the question?
Okay.
Ladies and gentlemen, please give it up to Amanda Silver.